<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two epistles, written to all Friends in the truth the one touching the perfection of humility, written in Rome-prison of madmen, the other touching the righteous order of judgement in Israel, written at Lyons in France / by the servant of God, John.</title>
            <author>J. P. (John Perrot), d. 1671?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3555</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13192276</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13192276</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98383</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54448)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98383)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 433:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two epistles, written to all Friends in the truth the one touching the perfection of humility, written in Rome-prison of madmen, the other touching the righteous order of judgement in Israel, written at Lyons in France / by the servant of God, John.</title>
                  <author>J. P. (John Perrot), d. 1671?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Perrot. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Friends' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgment Day --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Humility --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO EPISTLES, Written to all Friends in the Truth: The one, touching the <hi>Perfection</hi> of HUMILITY; Written in <hi>Rome-Priſon</hi> of Madmen.</p>
            <p>The Other, Touching the RIGHTEOUS ORDER OF JUDGEMENT IN ISRAEL.</p>
            <p>Written at <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> By the Servant of God, <hi>JOHN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Windmil,</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:98383:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98383:2"/>
            <head>CONCERNING HUMILITY</head>
            <head type="sub">JOHN the Priſoner, to the Little LAMBS, SALUTATION.</head>
            <p>GOD Almighty is <hi>greater</hi> than the <hi>ſwelling</hi> and <hi>boyling Waves</hi> of a <hi>troubled, angry, raging Sea;</hi> for though ſhe <hi>rouls</hi> the unſetledneſs of her <hi>Outrage</hi> as the Tumblings of <hi>Mountain</hi> after <hi>Mountain;</hi> yet He which ruleth on high (ordering [in his unſearchable Counſel] all things for the <hi>Advantage</hi> of good <hi>Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> of all the <hi>conſtant, ſetled</hi> &amp; <hi>faithful-hearted;</hi> whoſe <hi>Delight,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>weariſomeneſs,</hi> is to truſt in his <hi>Living Name,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Supream Power</hi>) can make all in a moment, and turning of a ſhort ſpace, become as <hi>ſtanding Oyl.</hi> Thus ſaith the <hi>Voice</hi> which is <hi>holy,</hi> which is <hi>true,</hi> which is <hi>living</hi> and <hi>faithful;</hi> Who hath <hi>Power</hi> but the <hi>LORD?</hi> Or, where is there <hi>permiſſion</hi> but of the <hi>Mighty One?</hi> Where is <hi>Counſel</hi> but with the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Wiſdom,</hi> who <hi>purgeth Jacob</hi> in his way, and <hi>befooleth</hi> his <hi>Foes</hi> in the very <hi>open wayes,</hi> and <hi>narroweſt</hi> and <hi>ſecreteſt paths</hi> of their own <hi>Outgoings</hi> and <hi>Deſigns?</hi> Who hath <hi>known</hi> the <hi>LORD,</hi> and will not <hi>truſt</hi> in Him for an <hi>Everlaſting Good?</hi> Who hath <hi>truſted</hi> in the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Salvation,</hi> that can ſay <hi>his Truſt hath periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the end,</hi> and the <hi>peace</hi> of his <hi>ſoul</hi> is <hi>fled from him?</hi> Or, can his <hi>Servants</hi> ſay that He is <hi>as a man,</hi> or like unto the <hi>ſon of man</hi> which <hi>remembreth</hi> not the <hi>way,</hi> nor <hi>enclineth</hi> unto the <hi>Cry</hi> of the <hi>Juſt?</hi> Verily, the <hi>Seas</hi> may <hi>ſink</hi> through the <hi>Earth,</hi> and be no more, as the Waters in her belly, and the <hi>whole Earth</hi> become as a <hi>whirled duſt</hi> out of a <hi>golden Ballance;</hi> Yet is there <hi>Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> with the <hi>Lord</hi> for <hi>Worm Jacob,</hi> and a <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> for <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Moreover, Though <hi>Nature</hi> may <hi>dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate</hi> from her proper kind, the <hi>Cow</hi> nor the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> the <hi>Camel</hi> nor the <hi>Old Lionneſs;</hi> nay, nor the <hi>Nurſe</hi> nor the <hi>Mother</hi> have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98383:3"/>
any more <hi>pitty</hi> or <hi>compaſſion</hi> to the <hi>fruits</hi> of their own <hi>bowels</hi> to <hi>ſuckle</hi> or <hi>nouriſh</hi> them in due ſeaſon, though <hi>they</hi> might <hi>harden</hi> their <hi>hearts,</hi> and <hi>ſhut</hi> their <hi>ears</hi> from the <hi>Cryes</hi> of their <hi>own fleſh,</hi> and ſhould <hi>loath</hi> and <hi>abominate</hi> their <hi>languiſhings</hi> unto <hi>death;</hi> yet is there <hi>Compaſſion</hi> with the <hi>God of David</hi> for the <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>contrite-hearted,</hi> and <hi>Deliverance</hi> with the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> for the <hi>Seed of his own Hoſt,</hi> though they are <hi>ſtraitned</hi> by the <hi>Red Sea-ſide:</hi> Therefore <hi>lift up your heads, <hi>O ye little Lambs,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>breath to your Keeper</hi> in the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>reverence, <hi>ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying</hi>
               </hi> his <hi>NAME <hi>in your hearts,</hi>
               </hi> in the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> until the <hi>Rod</hi> be ſtretched over the <hi>Floods;</hi> for then ſhall you <hi>march</hi> with <hi>dry ſhoes</hi> through the <hi>mighty deeps,</hi> with the <hi>Songs</hi> of <hi>Salvation</hi> in <hi>your Way;</hi> But the <hi>joyning hands</hi> of the <hi>divided Waters</hi> will cover the <hi>running ſtones</hi> of the <hi>Defences</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as <hi>Rocks</hi> that are caſt to the <hi>bottoms; doubled</hi> then ſhall your <hi>Pſalms</hi> be, <hi>Yea,</hi> and <hi>trebly tuned</hi> unto the higheſt <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of Him which <hi>rules</hi> in the <hi>Heavens above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Day</hi> wherein God Almighty is <hi>trying</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> with what <hi>an eye</hi> you are <hi>enclined</hi> to look into the <hi>Life</hi> of his <hi>humility,</hi> who ſhews himſelf as <hi>a ſervant</hi> unto <hi>Man,</hi> walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Corn-fields,</hi> and attending him with <hi>Bread</hi> and all things; who <hi>feeds</hi> the <hi>Worms</hi> of the <hi>workmanſhip</hi> of his hands, and <hi>refreſheth</hi> the <hi>creeping things</hi> with the <hi>lowly</hi> and <hi>humble At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance</hi> of his <hi>own moſt infinit bowels of Mercies;</hi> yea, he <hi>walks</hi> in the <hi>deeps</hi> of the <hi>Seas,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Worms</hi> that <hi>creep</hi> in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of her belly and womb, <hi>watching</hi> and <hi>waiting</hi> as the <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> of <hi>all diligence</hi> to <hi>ſerve <hi>them</hi>
               </hi> in <hi>all wants.</hi> Ah! what ſhall I ſay of the King of <hi>Glory,</hi> to whom the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> are but as a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> and the <hi>Firmament</hi> of the <hi>Heavens</hi> but as a <hi>dark</hi> and <hi>gloomy vail?</hi> Surely, when I conſider the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>moſt Eternally <hi>glorious,</hi>
               </hi> full of <hi>Wiſdom, Strength, Power, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, Light</hi> and <hi>Brightneſs</hi> (the height of whoſe Majeſty in all things which <hi>glorious</hi> are, there's no end of ſpace to reach) how He hath <hi>humbled <hi>Himſelf</hi>
               </hi> to come down in the <hi>lowlineſs</hi> of his <hi>Life,</hi> to <hi>ſerve me</hi> (his diſpiſed of man) with the <hi>greatneſs</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> of His <hi>rich Compaſſions,</hi> it <hi>moves</hi> and <hi>melts</hi> my <hi>heart</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and even now makes me <hi>cry</hi> in the Spirit, ſaying, Oh that the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the <hi>moſt wiſe</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> would encreaſe with me for ever, to the end, <hi>inſtructing</hi> me to <hi>ſerve,</hi> as He
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98383:3"/>
               <hi>ſerveth</hi> in the <hi>humbleneſs</hi> of his <hi>wiſeſt Life.</hi> Children this is the <hi>deep place</hi> where you are to <hi>ſink down into,</hi> in this the day of the <hi>tryal</hi> of <hi>ſpirits,</hi> to know of what nature they are: So here, <hi>try <hi>your ſelves,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>prove <hi>your ſelves,</hi>
               </hi> and ſee if you can <hi>ſerve</hi> the <hi>Worms</hi> of God, which <hi>creep</hi> upon the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>Earth</hi> (even as God <hi>ſerveth</hi> them) according to the <hi>meaſure</hi> and <hi>proportion</hi> of the <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>knowledge</hi> which from God you have <hi>received; <hi>ſearch</hi>
               </hi> your <hi>ſelves,</hi> and <hi>examine</hi> your <hi>ſelves,</hi> whether in <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>true kind</hi> you can <hi>ſerve,</hi> as <hi>God Almighty <hi>ſerveth,</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>poor creeping things;</hi> or ſerve <hi>Lazarus</hi> the poor man, as <hi>God Eternal</hi> ſerved him in <hi>Dogs,</hi> and the World ſaw it not: Yea, and <hi>queſtion</hi> your ſelves, and <hi>try your hearts,</hi> that you may <hi>know,</hi> whether you can <hi>ſerve</hi> God in that <hi>lowlineſs</hi> in which <hi>He</hi> daily <hi>ſerveth you;</hi> and ſo <hi>conſider well</hi> how <hi>God Almighty</hi> provideth your <hi>food</hi> and <hi>rayment,</hi> and puts the <hi>bread</hi> in your <hi>mouths,</hi> and pours the <hi>water</hi> into <hi>your cups,</hi> and <hi>arrays</hi> you, and <hi>latches your ſhoes,</hi> and <hi>makes clean</hi> the <hi>filthy way</hi> before your <hi>footſteps;</hi> And if any among you have <hi>griefs</hi> or <hi>ſores,</hi> or <hi>botches</hi> or <hi>painful boyls,</hi> God Almighty <hi>humbleth</hi> his <hi>compaſſionate Soul,</hi> and <hi>cometh down</hi> from <hi>on high,</hi> and ſtands exceedingly <hi>below you,</hi> where you <hi>ſee him not,</hi> and putteth out <hi>his tongue,</hi> and <hi>licketh</hi> your <hi>ſore places,</hi> and ſo <hi>healeth</hi> the <hi>wounded,</hi> and <hi>ſaveth</hi> the <hi>ſick</hi> from the <hi>grief</hi> of the <hi>malady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh my <hi>Beloved Ones!</hi> and <hi>deareſt <hi>little Children</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Lambs</hi> of God, I cannot tell you how infinitly you own <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Father</hi> ſtandeth <hi>below you,</hi> and round about you, <hi>waiting</hi> and <hi>watching</hi> in <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>loving-kindneſs</hi> to <hi>ſerve</hi> you, whoſe <hi>day</hi> this is, which now is, wherein you muſt be <hi>tryed</hi> and <hi>proved,</hi> whether you <hi>bear</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> of his holy Spirit of <hi>Humility,</hi> as did <hi>Jeſus</hi> the <hi>Juſt;</hi> and as you are found <hi>ſinking down</hi> here into the <hi>low place,</hi> even in admiration, conſidering where (before this day) you dwelt in a houſe which had its Foundation above the <hi>Rocks</hi> of the deeps of the <hi>low places,</hi> whereon the <hi>higheſt Heavens</hi> are pitched, and therefore <hi>All</hi> muſt <hi>ſink</hi> unto it and be <hi>firmly</hi> ſetled <hi>on it,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ye may know the <hi>boſom</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> from which all <hi>pure ſervice</hi> doth proceed; <hi>ſervice <hi>to God,</hi> ſervice <hi>to man,</hi> ſervice <hi>to beaſts,</hi> ſervice <hi>to fowls,</hi> ſervice <hi>to fiſhes</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>ſervice <hi>to worms,</hi>
               </hi> all in the <hi>Love,</hi> in which they were by the <hi>humble Spirit</hi> created, to be <hi>ſerved</hi> of the <hi>humble Spirit,</hi> according to all their <hi>reſpective kinds;</hi> So here you may ſee the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> dwelleth in the <hi>low place,</hi> where a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98383:4"/>
               <hi>friend</hi> in the pure Spirit of <hi>Humility</hi> (which proceedeth out of the Eternal Boſom of Love, which created all things for a ſervice, as God Almighty himſelf ſerveth all living creatures in the ſame Love and Lowlineſs) oughteth to <hi>ſweep his friend's houſe</hi> and to <hi>latch his ſhoes,</hi> and <hi>make clean the way of his footſteps,</hi> yea, and <hi>to do it</hi> with the <hi>very ſweat of his brow;</hi> which I ſpeak in God Almighty's holy Spirit <hi>to all</hi> without <hi>respect of perſons;</hi> For this will give all the <hi>Children</hi> true entrance and <hi>living ingreſs</hi> into the <hi>bowels</hi> of <hi>God's mercies,</hi> that as they (in the incomprehenſible Love) are come down <hi>to ſerve</hi> in the <hi>low houſe,</hi> beneath all <hi>Earth,</hi> and <hi>Waters</hi> under the <hi>Earth,</hi> and there to give <hi>due attendance</hi> as God Almighty <hi>wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> to <hi>ſerve all;</hi> and thus are <hi>Miniſters</hi> in the <hi>feeling bowels</hi> of the <hi>unlimited pitties</hi> and <hi>compaſſions</hi> to all <hi>diſtreſſes,</hi> without <hi>reſpect</hi> of <hi>creatures</hi> or <hi>perſons;</hi> in this manner gathering all into the <hi>unlimited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of their <hi>bowels</hi> of <hi>mercies;</hi> So become, they <hi>gathered</hi> into the <hi>inmoſt part</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Boſom;</hi> and here the <hi>Life</hi> provoketh the <hi>Love,</hi> and the <hi>Love</hi> ſtirreth up the <hi>Bowels,</hi> and the <hi>Bowels</hi> of God are provoked <hi>to yearn <hi>in Himſelf,</hi>
               </hi> which brings <hi>home</hi> the <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> of the <hi>Oppreſſed</hi> in a greater weight upon the Spirit of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, than if it were done to him alone, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; for that they are the <hi>helpleſs Apple</hi> of his <hi>Eye,</hi> which cannot help it ſelf, nor take out the <hi>pricking motes</hi> without the <hi>help</hi> of a <hi>careful</hi> and <hi>merciful hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore the <hi>GOD</hi> of your <hi>Hope</hi> (in the day of Affliction and Temptation) will <hi>ariſe</hi> and <hi>roar</hi> as <hi>a Lioneſs</hi> which <hi>is robbed of her Whelps,</hi> becauſe <hi>her compaſſions</hi> go after <hi>her young;</hi> and the <hi>Nations</hi> ſhall <hi>dread</hi> and <hi>tremble,</hi> and the <hi>Hoſt</hi> thereof <hi>ſhall fall</hi> by the <hi>high-way ſide;</hi> for as much as they carried away the <hi>ſpoil</hi> which they ſhould have <hi>left in the Land,</hi> and have <hi>waſted</hi> the <hi>Tents</hi> of the <hi>Lord:</hi> And the <hi>houſe</hi> of the <hi>Spoiler</hi> ſhall be made <hi>a ſpoil</hi> before <hi>Him,</hi> and he which <hi>robbed</hi> the <hi>Labourer</hi> of his <hi>Hemp</hi> and <hi>Flax,</hi> as he <hi>beareth</hi> the <hi>burden</hi> thereof from his <hi>Neighbours</hi> door, it ſhall <hi>burn</hi> as a <hi>flame</hi> at his <hi>back. <hi>Wo</hi>
               </hi> unto <hi>Egypt,</hi> for the Lord <hi>is jealous: <hi>Wo</hi>
               </hi> unto <hi>Rimmon,</hi> for that the <hi>Anger</hi> of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Judgment kindleth; <hi>Weep</hi>
               </hi> ye <hi>craggy Rocks,</hi> and <hi>howl</hi> ye <hi>exalted Mountains,</hi> and <hi>lament</hi> your <hi>part,</hi> O ye <hi>lofty Hills</hi> round about the <hi>Cities</hi> of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon;</hi> For I will <hi>overturn</hi> ſaith the Lord God, and it ſhall be a day of <hi>ratling,</hi> even as if the <hi>Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> were <hi>falling</hi> with <hi>Thunders;</hi> Nations ſhall hear it and <hi>dread,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98383:4"/>
and I will have a <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſaith the Lord Almighty, even unto the ends of the whole earth. Then ſhalt thou ſing O <hi>Daughter</hi> of my <hi>own Beloved,</hi> and <hi>gladneſs</hi> ſhall never depart from thy <hi>Scituation,</hi> O <hi>Damſel</hi> of my <hi>hearts delight;</hi> for I will <hi>be thine</hi> in <hi>an Oath,</hi> and thou ſhalt <hi>be mine</hi> in a <hi>perpetual Covenant,</hi> even for <hi>ever</hi> and <hi>evermore,</hi> ſaith the God of <hi>eternal love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>this Spirit</hi> therefore (which is of Power &amp; Might, of Truth and Faithfulneſs) I have <hi>dearly</hi> to <hi>ſtir you up,</hi> and <hi>exhort you,</hi> to <hi>wait</hi> in the <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>content</hi> of the <hi>Life</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> ſubmitting in the will of the Father unto <hi>every yoak, weight</hi> and <hi>burthen</hi> whatſoever, may be permitted to be put upon your <hi>necks</hi> and <hi>backs:</hi> and alſo in the true <hi>feeling</hi> of the <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> of <hi>every ſoul,</hi> put your <hi>backs</hi> to their <hi>burthen,</hi> whoſoever <hi>they be,</hi> without <hi>reſpect</hi> of <hi>perſons;</hi> for that Spirit is of God which is <hi>tender,</hi> and enclineth unto a <hi>feeling</hi> of <hi>every mans Yoak;</hi> for ſo did God Almighty <hi>feel,</hi> and <hi>pity,</hi> and <hi>compaſſionate</hi> them in their <hi>Sufferings,</hi> and under their <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> which now <hi>do oppreſſe,</hi> and make the others to <hi>ſuffer</hi> by <hi>whom</hi> they formerly <hi>were oppreſſed;</hi> which the <hi>others</hi> ſhould not <hi>have done <hi>then,</hi>
               </hi> neither ſhould theſe do ſo <hi>now;</hi> Therefore <hi>do ye,</hi> the Children of God, even as your Father <hi>doth,</hi> ſtand between them both in the Spirit, which bears every man's <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>unjuſt load,</hi> and ſo you ſhew your ſelves to be of the <hi>Image</hi> of your <hi>Father,</hi> who thereby will enlarge his Glory very greatly in the whole Earth; for God will have ſuch <hi>a ſound</hi> to go unto the <hi>ends</hi> thereof, and gain himſelf <hi>a great Name</hi> of <hi>praiſe</hi> thereby: And as for you in <hi>this Spirit,</hi> your <hi>Reward</hi> ſhall be <hi>very great,</hi> and your <hi>Redemption</hi> ſhall <hi>certainly come;</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore again, I ſay let <hi>Patience</hi> have her <hi>perfect work;</hi> for the <hi>black horſe</hi> which is <hi>Coloured over <hi>with blood,</hi>
               </hi> which <hi>now <hi>runneth the race,</hi>
               </hi> was never <hi>truly ayred,</hi> nor well <hi>breathed,</hi> and the <hi>Courſe</hi> from the <hi>firſt ſtart,</hi> being <hi>a full looſe</hi> upon <hi>ſwitch</hi> and <hi>ſpur,</hi> will <hi>ſurely ſink,</hi> before <hi>half</hi> the <hi>Race</hi> is <hi>run;</hi> and he which comes <hi>gently <hi>after</hi>
               </hi> on the <hi>moderate <hi>ſpeed</hi>
               </hi> will <hi>obtain</hi> the <hi>mark</hi> and the <hi>prize.</hi> So though the <hi>little ones</hi> do eat <hi>their bread</hi> with the <hi>ſweat</hi> of their brows for a ſeaſon, it is but to <hi>prepare them,</hi> and <hi>their pure appetites</hi> to eat at a <hi>feaſt</hi> of <hi>fat things</hi> in the <hi>infinite worth,</hi> and <hi>incomprehenſible price</hi> of an <hi>everlaſting life</hi> of <hi>thanksgiving</hi> and <hi>praiſe</hi> unto <hi>him</hi> which <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which <hi>purpoſe,</hi> this the Lord God <hi>requireth</hi> of his <hi>People, <hi>rent</hi> ſouls, <hi>broken</hi> ſpirits, <hi>contrite</hi> hearts, <hi>breathing</hi> mindes, <hi>fervent</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98383:5"/>
and <hi>exceeding <hi>open</hi> bowels</hi> to <hi>God Almighty,</hi> in <hi>all things</hi> of <hi>your ſouls deſires;</hi> for this is <hi>the <hi>Sacrifice</hi>
               </hi> which <hi>the Eternal Power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth</hi> from <hi>All</hi> without <hi>respect</hi> of <hi>perſons,</hi> and he <hi>loveth</hi> the <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſpirit,</hi> and hath <hi>respect</hi> unto the <hi>contrite heart,</hi> which I <hi>full well know</hi> by <hi>large teſtimony</hi> and <hi>experience;</hi> and now, the deeper I <hi>ponder it,</hi> the more <hi>it rents my inward parts,</hi> to conſider the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which <hi>anſwereth</hi> the <hi>full ſtreams</hi> of the <hi>broken ſpirit</hi> and <hi>contrite heart,</hi> which I cannot but teſtifie, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> may <hi>drink refreſhment</hi> even at the <hi>brim</hi> of the <hi>Cup-ful</hi> of my <hi>Conſolations,</hi> and hold it as an exceeding <hi>Joy</hi> in his houſe, to <hi>go down</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> himſelf before <hi>his God</hi> in the <hi>rent <hi>ſoul,</hi> broken <hi>ſpirit,</hi>
               </hi> and exceeding <hi>contrite <hi>heart,</hi>
               </hi> to feel his <hi>Creator's acceptance</hi> of <hi>him</hi> in the day of his <hi>mourning</hi> before him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enter, enter,</hi> and <hi>feel</hi> your <hi>thorough <hi>ingreſs</hi>
               </hi> into <hi>this houſe</hi> in the <hi>contrite heart,</hi> O all ye <hi>Children of the living God,</hi> that you may <hi>know</hi> your <hi>Father's Life,</hi> and bear his <hi>very Image</hi> and <hi>true likeneſs</hi> in <hi>all things;</hi> for <hi>his Spirit</hi> is <hi>wounded,</hi> and <hi>mourneth</hi> and <hi>grieveth,</hi> (in more contriteneſs than your eye can diſcern or reach) bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every man's <hi>oppreſſive burdens,</hi> without <hi>respect</hi> of <hi>perſons:</hi> ſo you <hi>entring</hi> here into the <hi>deeps</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, the <hi>humble ſpirit</hi> of <hi>contriteneſs,</hi> you move the <hi>bowels</hi> of your <hi>Maker,</hi> and his <hi>bowels</hi> ſtir up <hi>his Power</hi> to <hi>return</hi> the <hi>Captivity</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> and of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe lot is to <hi>inhabit Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be it known unto you all, That <hi>God Almighty</hi> will be <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry</hi> with all ſuch which do <hi>ſtand</hi> in a <hi>height</hi> (above the <hi>contrite</hi> and <hi>broken heart</hi>) ſaying in preſumption, <hi>We are above and beyond all things in the outward which can annoy or hurt us,</hi> and God will <hi>bring down</hi> all <hi>ſuch,</hi> and make them <hi>to know</hi> that if <hi>he is lived in,</hi> he will be <hi>lived in,</hi> even in <hi>his Spirit</hi> of <hi>contriteneſs,</hi> which <hi>infuſeth</hi> the <hi>reverence,</hi> and <hi>fear, dread</hi> and <hi>trembling</hi> at <hi>his Name</hi> in the <hi>inward parts,</hi> where the <hi>broken heart</hi> muſt be <hi>witneſſed,</hi> which is the <hi>true ſacrifice</hi> which God <hi>requireth</hi> and <hi>accepteth:</hi> So he that is gone above the <hi>contrite heart</hi> is gone out of the <hi>acceptance</hi> with God, not having the <hi>true Sacrifice</hi> in which <hi>acceptance is found,</hi> and in that <hi>heart</hi> which is gone from the <hi>contriteneſs</hi> there is no <hi>true praiſe;</hi> for the <hi>low life is departed</hi> from, which only can <hi>praiſe Him</hi> which ruleth above all things, and ſo the <hi>creature</hi> goeth from his <hi>Creator</hi> and <hi>ſacrificeth</hi> unto his own <hi>affection,</hi> and <hi>praiſeth</hi> the <hi>delight</hi> of his <hi>own luſt,</hi> and <hi>drowneth</hi> his <hi>poor ſoul</hi> in <hi>perdition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98383:5"/>Finally, my <hi>dear</hi> and <hi>everlaſtingly beloved <hi>little Lambs</hi>
               </hi> of the <hi>true Shepherd,</hi> in this Spirit my life <hi>labours</hi> with <hi>you,</hi> and the <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance</hi> of <hi>my unſpeakable love</hi> floweth forth <hi>unto you,</hi> even that which <hi>no Voice</hi> can <hi>tell you</hi> but the <hi>immediate Voice</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which is <hi>nigh you;</hi> wherein I am <hi>rouled, bound up</hi> and <hi>ſealed <hi>among</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>in you,</hi> greatly <hi>comforted</hi> concerning <hi>you,</hi> feeling a <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>goodly num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> (in my daily prayers) of <hi>great price</hi> in the <hi>gracious eye of God;</hi> And many will <hi>paſſe</hi> thorough a <hi>fire</hi> which will make them <hi>ſhine</hi> as the <hi>Sun,</hi> and their fruit will be only to God.</p>
            <p>Ah! I cannot tell you of the <hi>Glory</hi> of the Day which cometh among you, for I am <hi>raviſhed</hi> and <hi>overcome</hi> in the <hi>ſence</hi> of that <hi>Glory,</hi> which my <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>bleared eye</hi> can <hi>ſee;</hi> and truly the <hi>Glory</hi> is <hi>ſuch,</hi> that <hi>for Glory</hi> I cannot behold, but <hi>I cry,</hi> but <hi>I cry,</hi> Oh! the <hi>depths</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> which will <hi>wound <hi>Enmity!</hi>
               </hi> Oh! the <hi>weight</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> which will <hi>kill <hi>Cruelty!</hi>
               </hi> Oh! the <hi>pleaſantneſs</hi> of <hi>Patience</hi> which will <hi>extinguiſh <hi>Perſecution!</hi>
               </hi> Oh! the <hi>depth</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> which will <hi>work over <hi>Stratagems!</hi>
               </hi> Oh! the <hi>worth</hi> of <hi>Vertue,</hi> which will <hi>crown</hi> with <hi>Diadems!</hi> Oh! the <hi>dread</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> which will <hi>wear</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of an <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dominion!</hi> this will be the <hi>Sting,</hi> the <hi>Wo</hi> and the <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> unto every <hi>unclean ſpirit</hi> upon the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> until ſhe ſhall <hi>bear</hi> that ſpirit <hi>no more</hi> upon her <hi>face,</hi> but all things ſhall be as they <hi>were</hi> in the <hi>beginning,</hi> and God in more <hi>infinite meaſure</hi> gloriouſly <hi>known</hi> and <hi>enjoyed,</hi> than ever in any Age that is paſt ſince the dayes that <hi>Adam</hi> was made a true and living Soul. <hi>Grace, Mercy and Peace be unto you all, giving you growth in this Life.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <q>So reade me in the Word of God, and then reade this a ſecond time over in your Congregations.</q>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Written in</hi> Rome-Priſon <hi>of Mad-men.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98383:6"/>
            <head>Concerning Judgment.</head>
            <head type="sub">The <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Love, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Unity,</hi> who is of the mind of <hi>Subjection</hi> unto the <hi>Spirits</hi> of the <hi>Prophets;</hi> To the <hi>Gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Seed</hi> of the <hi>Lord Almighty,</hi> Sendeth the <hi>Fruits</hi> of the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Concord,</hi> as a moſt <hi>ſincere Salutation,</hi> unto them <hi>all,</hi> whereſoever upon the face of the Earth.</head>
            <p>BEloved <hi>Siſters</hi> and <hi>Brethren,</hi> I would that you ſhould <hi>all know,</hi> in the <hi>deeps</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> and Glory, that GOD is but <hi>one <hi>Eternal Life</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Love, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Everlaſting <hi>Unity</hi>
               </hi> in <hi>Himſelf,</hi> not having in Him <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice,</hi> ſtrength of a <hi>froward Will, luſt</hi> of <hi>entrance</hi> into <hi>any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> than His <hi>own,</hi> or <hi>Pride</hi> in His <hi>Throne of Glory;</hi> but is <hi>full</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Mercies</hi> unto <hi>Enemies, <hi>eaſie</hi>
               </hi> to be <hi>entreated of; <hi>Pure</hi>
               </hi> in <hi>Life,</hi> and the <hi>loweſt</hi> and <hi>humbleſt <hi>in His Eternal mind,</hi>
               </hi> of all <hi>things</hi> beſide <hi>Him;</hi> Yea, as He is <hi>Infinitely</hi> in Power <hi>above all</hi> the <hi>works</hi> of his <hi>hands,</hi> ſo in His <hi>Humility</hi> He is <hi>Immeaſurably <hi>below</hi>
               </hi> them <hi>all,</hi> wherein the <hi>Excellency</hi> of His <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> is <hi>ſeen</hi> to be <hi>above all,</hi> who is <hi>bleſſed, praiſed,</hi> and <hi>honoured</hi> of <hi>all</hi> that truly <hi>know Him,</hi> for ever, Amen.</p>
            <p>This therefore is <hi>His mind,</hi> unto <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>the Day,</hi> (viz.) <hi>That they ſhould ſeek to have a <hi>dwelling</hi> in the brightneſs <hi>of the Glory</hi> of His <hi>Life,</hi>
               </hi> by <hi>feeling</hi> after Him in the <hi>loweſt places</hi> of His <hi>habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> where <hi>righteous Judges</hi> in <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be <hi>known,</hi> and <hi>righteous Judgement</hi> (which <hi>oppreſſeth</hi> not <hi>any,</hi> but is <hi>appointed</hi> for the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> unto <hi>all</hi>) ſhall be <hi>witneſſed</hi> in the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>raiſed Seed</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> which ſhall <hi>preſerve</hi> the <hi>Concord, Peace, Love,</hi> and <hi>everlaſting <hi>Unity</hi>
               </hi> among <hi>all,</hi> even unto the <hi>determination</hi> of <hi>all Time;</hi> wherein the <hi>Reſtoration</hi> of <hi>all things</hi> ſhall come <hi>to paſs,</hi> as it was <hi>firſt</hi> in the <hi>Original,</hi> before <hi>Tranſgreſſion</hi> was; that there may not be <hi>the groan</hi> of a <hi>Creature</hi> under the <hi>bondage</hi> of <hi>Oppreſſion;</hi> but the whole <hi>Earth, Seas,</hi> and <hi>all that in them is,</hi> become <hi>one entire
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98383:6"/>
Body,</hi> made <hi>up</hi> of the <hi>perfection</hi> of the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Almighty Creator,</hi> that it may be an <hi>everlaſting Song,</hi> of His <hi>higheſt Honour</hi> for <hi>ever</hi> and <hi>ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>I feel a <hi>Life,</hi> which in ſome years ſilence (through <hi>Tribulations</hi> and great <hi>Tribulations</hi>) in the ſecret continual <hi>exerciſe</hi> of the <hi>mind</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>holineſs,</hi> through the <hi>deep mercies of God,</hi> hath <hi>attained</hi> unto a <hi>ſmall meaſure</hi> of the <hi>underſtanding</hi> and <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of its <hi>Maker:</hi> And therefore as <hi>one</hi> that hath obtained <hi>Mercy</hi> at the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and is <hi>precepted</hi> to the <hi>ſame,</hi> am <hi>drawn forth</hi> of a <hi>free heart,</hi> to ſhew unto <hi>all the tender</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> That <hi>Order of Iudgement</hi> which is <hi>juſtified <hi>of the Lord God;</hi>
               </hi> that in the <hi>executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof,</hi> without <hi>reſpect</hi> of <hi>Perſons</hi> in <hi>Judgement,</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>his God</hi>'s <hi>Holineſs,</hi> may be <hi>kept</hi> in his <hi>Tents;</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Unity,</hi> in the <hi>richeſt bleſſings</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> be <hi>held</hi> and <hi>retained</hi> in his <hi>Land <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that are <hi>born</hi> of the <hi>Seed of Promiſe,</hi> muſt <hi>grow</hi> into the <hi>ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> of the <hi>glory</hi> of their <hi>heavenly Father</hi> in <hi>all things,</hi> which are <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>vertuous</hi> in the <hi>light</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> which gives <hi>to ſee</hi> that <hi>God</hi> is <hi>not <hi>rigorous, raſh,</hi>
               </hi> nor <hi>cruel;</hi> but <hi>tender, pitiful, forgiving, long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,</hi> and <hi>merciful;</hi> which ſheweth the <hi>amiableneſs</hi> of <hi>His Glory</hi> in <hi>Judgment,</hi> in which <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> all the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> muſt <hi>grow</hi> to be as their <hi>Father</hi> is; for which <hi>Cauſe</hi> in matters of <hi>unreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedneſs</hi> or <hi>controverſie</hi> betwixt <hi>Friend</hi> and <hi>Friend, Brother</hi> &amp; <hi>Brother,</hi> it ought to be <hi>pondered,</hi> Whether the <hi>thing</hi> that is <hi>objected</hi> againſt, <hi>be ſin?</hi> which if it ſo <hi>appears,</hi> and that alſo to the <hi>diſhonour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>his Truth</hi> in the <hi>eye of the World,</hi> then ſhall there be <hi>an utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of the ſin,</hi> and <hi>a tender admonition</hi> given <hi>to that Perſon</hi> to <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake</hi> and <hi>repent of his ſin:</hi> And ſo like wiſe <hi>Gardeners,</hi> ye ought to <hi>pluck up</hi> the <hi>Weeds,</hi> that the <hi>Plants</hi> may <hi>proſper</hi> in the <hi>ground,</hi> and <hi>prune</hi> the <hi>Tree,</hi> cutting off the <hi>unprofitable branches,</hi> that the <hi>profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> may <hi>much more proſper,</hi> yeilding <hi>abundance of fruit,</hi> in <hi>due ſeaſon,</hi> unto the <hi>Lord</hi> of the <hi>Vineyard;</hi> and not go too <hi>haſtily</hi> and cut off a <hi>Twig,</hi> becauſe of a <hi>corrupted leaf thereon,</hi> nor cut off <hi>a Limb</hi> of the <hi>Tree</hi> becauſe of <hi>a withered bow on the Limb;</hi> but rather <hi>learn</hi> the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Righteouſniſs</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> in caſes of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>uncleanneſs,</hi> to <hi>ſtoop down and write with the finger on the ground,</hi> and when you have <hi>ſufficiently written there; as the Lamb ſtooped down twice</hi> in the <hi>Judgement</hi> of the <hi>cauſe</hi> of the <hi>Harlot,</hi> then you will come to lift up the head alſo, (as he did) and ſay, <hi>Go thy way, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98383:7"/>
                  <hi>ſin no more;</hi>
               </hi> for by <hi>ſtooping down</hi> and <hi>writing on the ground,</hi> you will put <hi>many</hi> in the <hi>way,</hi> wherein they will <hi>ſin no more;</hi> as the <hi>Lamb</hi> (your Example) <hi>did</hi> the <hi>Adultereſs:</hi> And <hi>there</hi> you will be <hi>known</hi> to be of <hi>His Spirit,</hi> which taketh away <hi>the ſin of the world,</hi> and not made as <hi>Inſtruments</hi> to the <hi>cutting off</hi> of <hi>ſouls</hi> from <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> cauſing them thereby to turn <hi>into all ſin</hi> and <hi>uncleanneſs;</hi> neither will the <hi>grief</hi> of the <hi>Juſt</hi> fall <hi>juſtly upon your heads,</hi> nor the <hi>ſore diſtractions</hi> of the <hi>oppreſſed</hi> become <hi>your Burthens,</hi> but <hi>Peace <hi>will be with you for ever:</hi>
               </hi> But until <hi>this order of the Judgement <hi>of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> be throughly among you,</hi> God will make <hi>Whips <hi>for the daughters of Judah,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Scourges <hi>for the ſons of Iſrael,</hi>
               </hi> and in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>chaſtize <hi>His People,</hi>
               </hi> until they are <hi>formed</hi> into the <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of the <hi>brightneſs</hi> of His <hi>Glory,</hi> in the true <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>His Judgements</hi> and <hi>Mercies,</hi> which go over all <hi>His Works;</hi> to be made a <hi>perfect Inheritance</hi> unto Him for <hi>ever,</hi> as He is <hi>their God,</hi> and their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;</hi> But after <hi>Admonition</hi> upon <hi>Admonition, Reproof</hi> upon <hi>Reproof,</hi> if ſuch <hi>a Perſon</hi> as is <hi>ſpoken of,</hi> ſtoppeth the <hi>Ear,</hi> and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the <hi>Heart,</hi> and deſpiſeth the <hi>Way</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and will not be <hi>Converted</hi> and <hi>Healed,</hi> after all the <hi>gentle dealings</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>your Father,</hi> and the <hi>Lamb in you:</hi> Then it will <hi>appear juſt</hi> and <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi> in any <hi>Siſter</hi> or <hi>Brother,</hi> that is <hi>moved</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in his <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>holy Fear,</hi> in the <hi>Spirit of Sobriety,</hi> to <hi>Judge <hi>the evil</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>one,</hi> in ſuch <hi>ſeverity</hi> as the <hi>Brother</hi> or <hi>Siſter</hi> may be led unto <hi>by the Spirit of Widom</hi> to do; and ſo the <hi>Judgement</hi> will <hi>ſtand true</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> never <hi>to be repented of,</hi> for it will <hi>reach</hi> to that <hi>of God in all,</hi> in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Truth,</hi> both in <hi>matter, time</hi> and <hi>manner.</hi> And as this <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Righteous Judgement</hi> is <hi>kept,</hi> ſo <hi>Peace</hi> will be <hi>alſo kept</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Unity of <hi>Love</hi> in <hi>all his Tents</hi> for <hi>Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be it known unto you, that <hi>Haſtineſs</hi> is <hi>not</hi> of the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>my Father,</hi> who <hi>wooeth <hi>ſinners,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>correcteth</hi> gently in <hi>meaſure,</hi> and <hi>ſtirreth</hi> up his <hi>Bowels</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Mercies, <hi>again</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>again</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>ſinners,</hi> and often <hi>wooeth</hi> a <hi>ſtiffnecked</hi> and <hi>rebellious enemy,</hi> and <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> a <hi>treacherous ſoul</hi> by the <hi>power</hi> of his <hi>boundleſs eternal <hi>Love:</hi>
               </hi> Wherefore <hi>all</hi> that are <hi>born of the Seed of his Kingdom,</hi> muſt <hi>ſo grow</hi> into the <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Similitude</hi> of <hi>their God,</hi> in his <hi>Spirit,</hi> of the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>Love, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering,</hi> and exceeding <hi>Tenderneſs</hi> unto <hi>one another,</hi> and unto <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Creation</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> made of His <hi>mighty hand,</hi> as that their <hi>lives</hi> may <hi>ſhew forth</hi> the <hi>excellency</hi> of His <hi>Praiſe</hi> in their <hi>Generation,</hi> even to the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>their dayes</hi> in the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98383:7"/>Again, in <hi>Caſes</hi> of <hi>Treſpaſſes</hi> of <hi>Brethren</hi> againſt <hi>Brethren,</hi> it <hi>ought</hi> to be <hi>looked into,</hi> whether the <hi>Treſpaſs</hi> was of a <hi>preſumptuous Will;</hi> &amp; find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it <hi>ſo,</hi> the <hi>Treſpaſſer</hi> may <hi>wiſely</hi> be <hi>dealt</hi> withal as <hi>aboveſaid;</hi> but ſtil the <hi>Brethren</hi> in ſuch <hi>caſes</hi> muſt mind <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> more than <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> Becauſe the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi> in the <hi>glorious Power</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Mercies,</hi> is <hi>able</hi> to <hi>overcome</hi> all the <hi>Treſpaſſes,</hi> and the <hi>ſtrong Will</hi> in <hi>all men</hi> which works <hi>Treſpaſſes.</hi> Wherefore <hi>he</hi> that <hi>overcomes</hi> in this <hi>manner,</hi> gains <hi>Victory</hi> in the <hi>Battel</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and ſo <hi>Conquers,</hi> as to <hi>receive</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Victory</hi> on his <hi>Head;</hi> and alſo to <hi>ſee plainly,</hi> how the <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> in <hi>him,</hi> covers a <hi>multitude</hi> of <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>evils:</hi> And may not I ſay unto <hi>you all</hi> (without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons) if my <hi>Eternal Father</hi> of <hi>brightneſs,</hi> gave you the <hi>Example</hi> of the <hi>Lamb</hi> of His <hi>Glory, in taking away the ſins of the World,</hi> ought not ye to be <hi>careful followers</hi> of <hi>Him</hi> in <hi>all</hi> His <hi>ſteps,</hi> preſſing on in the <hi>growth</hi> of His <hi>Spirit,</hi> as much <hi>as in you lies,</hi> to <hi>do,</hi> as he <hi>did?</hi> And if He, <hi>in the Love of the Father,</hi> took <hi>away</hi> the <hi>ſin of the World,</hi> whilſt yet it was in <hi>enmity</hi> to the <hi>Father,</hi> and His own <hi>Life,</hi> ought not ye <hi>therefore,</hi> earneſtly <hi>ſtrive</hi> to be <hi>careful,</hi> in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>remove</hi> the <hi>nature</hi> of a <hi>Treſpaſſe</hi> from a <hi>Brother?</hi> And know you not that the <hi>moſt Forgiveneſs</hi> is a <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>cauſe,</hi> for the <hi>ſtirring up</hi> of the <hi>moſt Love?</hi> and if <hi>Love</hi> be <hi>ſtirred up</hi> in <hi>this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> in the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>Treſpaſſers,</hi> through the <hi>obtaining</hi> from you <hi>the abundance of <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi>
               </hi> doth not this <hi>truly beget ſouls</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>nearneſs in God,</hi> who is the <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Fountain <hi>of Eternal Love and Forgiveneſs?</hi>
               </hi> Surely <hi>yea;</hi> And therefore, this is Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to you all, that you may be a <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>holy People</hi> to the <hi>Lord</hi> your <hi>God, <hi>Learn</hi> the Life of the Lamb, <hi>Follow</hi> Him whereſoever He goeth,</hi> and <hi>you ſhall never want <hi>Wiſdom</hi> nor <hi>Counſel</hi> in the Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to the end that you may all <hi>bear</hi> in your <hi>faces</hi> the <hi>expreſſe ſimilitude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> mind the Word of the Lord to the <hi>Revolted People</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who thus ſpake unto them by his Prophet, ſaying, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God</hi> [who is <hi>pittiful, merciful,</hi> and <hi>long-ſuffering; <hi>ſlow</hi>
               </hi> to <hi>anger,</hi> but <hi>ready <hi>to forgive</hi>] I delight not in the death of a ſinner, but rather that he might turn from his ſins and repent:</hi> Unto which <hi>Repentance</hi> the Lord God of Grace hath often <hi>wooed</hi> (as I have ſaid) <hi>perverſe Rebels,</hi> which have <hi>wilfully reſiſted</hi> his <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> and ſometimes hath <hi>ſmitten them</hi> with the <hi>Rod</hi> of his <hi>gentle Corrections,</hi> and then hath <hi>wooed</hi> them <hi>again,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>All the day long have I ſtretched
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98383:8"/>
out my hand to a gain-ſaying and rebellious People.</hi> And, Oh <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them that are ſent unto thee, How often would I have gathered thee as a Hen gathereth her Chickens, but ye would not?</hi> And which of us (this day in Sion) can ſay, but that <hi>our God</hi> ſent unto <hi>our ſouls <hi>Line</hi>
               </hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Line,</hi> and <hi>Precept</hi> upon <hi>Precept</hi> before we <hi>turned unto Him?</hi> and whilſt yet we were <hi>ſinners</hi> He loved us, and whilſt we were <hi>Enemies,</hi> He prepared the way of <hi>reconciling us</hi> unto <hi>Himſelf;</hi> and whilſt we were <hi>in our Blood</hi> He <hi>waſhed us;</hi> and when <hi>none eye pittied us</hi> His <hi>Mercies covered us:</hi> Now therefore if we ſhould <hi>deal</hi> by our <hi>Brethren</hi> which have <hi>halted</hi> by the <hi>way,</hi> and not in the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>dealings</hi> of our <hi>Father's love, mercies</hi> and <hi>compaſſions</hi> unto <hi>us</hi> whilſt yet we <hi>were enemies</hi> unto Him; then ſhould we <hi>degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> from the <hi>brightneſs</hi> of the <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of <hi>His Life,</hi> and be but as the <hi>ſons</hi> of <hi>darkneſs</hi> in <hi>Judgement;</hi> for in the <hi>Eternal ſweet Spirit of God</hi> I am ſure that <hi>all Judgement</hi> out of <hi>the Life</hi> of this <hi>Teſtimony</hi> is but for <hi>a day</hi> of <hi>reproof,</hi> and alſo to be <hi>tryed</hi> in <hi>a day</hi> of <hi>Revelation</hi> by <hi>Fire;</hi> and therefore the <hi>merciful Lamb of God,</hi> which taketh away the ſin of the world, ſaid, <hi>Judge not, leſt ye be judged;</hi> becauſe every <hi>tittle, out of his Spirit,</hi> is to be judged <hi>by his Spirit;</hi> ſince, in all Judgment beſides it, there is a <hi>ſecret ſeed</hi> of <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>enmity</hi> in the <hi>heart,</hi> which <hi>ſtirreth</hi> up <hi>prejudice</hi> in the hearts of the <hi>perſons judged;</hi> and ſuch <hi>judged ſouls</hi> by <hi>ſhyneſs</hi> and <hi>ſtrangeneſs</hi> kept at <hi>ſwords point,</hi> and at <hi>ſevere diſtance</hi> from <hi>Friends, <hi>hardens</hi>
               </hi> their hearts <hi>from God,</hi> which <hi>ſaves not,</hi> but <hi>deſtroys</hi> the <hi>ſoul:</hi> which is a <hi>ſore weight</hi> to fall upon <hi>any ſpirit (viz.)</hi> not to be an inſtrument of <hi>Salvation,</hi> but rather of <hi>Damnation;</hi> which for <hi>ten thouſand times ten thouſand</hi> the <hi>price</hi> of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> I would not ſhould <hi>fall justly</hi> upon my <hi>back</hi> through an <hi>act</hi> of the ſpirit of <hi>raſhneſs,</hi> unleſs firſt I had <hi>exhorted,</hi> ſecondly <hi>admoniſhed</hi> and <hi>meekly reproved;</hi> yea, after all <hi>this,</hi> if the perſon <hi>blameable</hi> ſhould ſtand <hi>in obſtinacy</hi> and <hi>perverſneſs</hi> of heart againſt God, even until the <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>utmoſt occaſion</hi> of <hi>denying</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſoul,</hi> I ought not to <hi>deliver</hi> ſuch a <hi>one over,</hi> but for the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> that the <hi>ſpirit</hi> may <hi>be ſaved</hi> in the day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>All Friends</hi> muſt take <hi>ſerious</hi> and <hi>prudent</hi> heed how they take up <hi>matters</hi> upon <hi>ſlight reports;</hi> for that is but of the ſame which is ready to ſay, <hi>Report,</hi> and <hi>we will report:</hi> for ſuch things will make <hi>Iſrael</hi> walk <hi>maimed</hi> in <hi>Counſel,</hi> and <hi>halt</hi> in <hi>Judgment,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98383:8"/>
and make him caſt the <hi>ſimple</hi> in the <hi>ditch,</hi> and ſet the <hi>ſubtil</hi> to fly <hi>ſwift</hi> over <hi>fences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, again I ſay, <hi>Be ye followers of the Lamb whereſoever he goeth;</hi> for he took the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>many,</hi> before he <hi>judged</hi> the <hi>Harlots Cauſe</hi> in the ſeat of Mercy.</p>
            <p>And be ye careful to take the <hi>advantage</hi> of <hi>countenancing</hi> and <hi>cheriſhing</hi> the <hi>leaſt appearance</hi> of <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Contrition</hi> of <hi>heart</hi> in any <hi>revolted ſoul,</hi> turning not your <hi>ear</hi> from it, but <hi>nouriſh it</hi> and <hi>cheriſh it</hi> in all, that ye may appear as <hi>ſtrength</hi> thereunto: And how know ye but that in <hi>ſo doing,</hi> ye may <hi>convert a ſinner to God,</hi> and <hi>turn him</hi> from the <hi>evil of his way?</hi> And will you not know <hi>in that day</hi> that there will <hi>be more Joy</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> among the <hi>Angels</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> than for the other <hi>ninety</hi> and <hi>nine</hi> of the <hi>Flock,</hi> which never <hi>erred</hi> nor <hi>ſtrayed</hi> from the <hi>Sheep-fold?</hi> And will not the ſence of the <hi>Joy</hi> of God's <hi>Angels</hi> be a <hi>ſufficient Crown</hi> of <hi>Reward</hi> unto you for ſo <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>bleſſed</hi> a work? Surely <hi>yea.</hi> And therefore my deareſt <hi>Siſters</hi> and <hi>Brethren,</hi> look ye to your <hi>Father,</hi> grow in his <hi>Image,</hi> and walk <hi>with Him;</hi> and <hi>bleſſed</hi> ſhall your <hi>Day</hi> be unto you for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am your Siſter in our Spouſe; <hi>JOHN.</hi>
               </signed>

            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Sent from <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> to be read by the Flock of the Lord every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: and not among the World, who pervert the Judgment of Truth.</p>
            </postscript>
            <postscript>
               <p>TOuching the fore-going <hi>Epiſtle</hi> I mention theſe few following words, for the prevention of the Worlds evil carping, and the exaltation of every ſpirit which hath erred, yet which hath ſeen the weakneſs of other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons judging them, and not according to the <hi>true order</hi> of the Judgment of the <hi>Lamb of God:</hi> To the <hi>World</hi> I ſay thus, Though a few, in Zeal, have ſtepped forth in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in a particular matter, ſomewhat beyond their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98383:9"/>
meaſures; yet becauſe of infirmity in ſuch a caſe are not to be caſt forth, and that becauſe of their <hi>Youth</hi> and <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs</hi> in the <hi>Truth,</hi> who in their this dayes birth, as new-born babes, have not yet attained unto the Perfection of that Wiſdom, which is to be attained unto, but through Experience are growing more and more into the ſame. And to perſons imprudently judged, this I alſo inſert, That if they from a ſence of this <hi>Admonition unto all,</hi> which reacheth unto ſuch <hi>young</hi> and <hi>zealous ſouls</hi> in the <hi>Truth</hi> which have imprudently judged them, ſhould riſe up and ſeek to boaſt over them, they would by it bring themſelves under the <hi>real Condemnation</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> which gave utterance of the aforeſaid <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> which only tends in ſubſtance for perfecting <hi>Unity, Peace</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> in God, which may never end.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
